Richard E. Lester fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
Richard E. Lester fonds
1963-1985
F-209
Q105668693
38 cm of textual records
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
Lester, Richard E.
Richard Lester was born in Toronto, Ontario in 1928. He came to Vancouver in 1947, eventually attending law school at the University of British Columbia. After being called to the British Columbia Bar in 1953 he practiced in Maple Ridge (then Haney). He served on the schoool board and was president of the BC School Trustees Association from 1961 to 1963.
In 1963 he was appointed to the first Board of Governors for the newly formed Simon Fraser University, a position he held until he became Chairman of the Board in the fall of 1968. He resigned this position in 1971, returning to his law practice.
Lester lived in Maple Ridge and then West Vancouver. He married Lois Audrey Jensen in 1952 and has 4 children.
published
Full
Published
Title based on contents of the fonds.
Fonds consists of records relating to Lester's time as a member of the Board of Governers and then the Chairman of the Board. The records are arranged in 3 series: Academic Freedom and Tenure, Correspondence, and Subject files. The subject files include records relating to the CAUT censure, the Department of Political Science, Sociology, and Anthropology (PSA) dispute, and university reorganization as a result of the censure and dispute.
Education
The fonds was donated by Richard Lester to the Simon Fraser University Archives.
Please consult the inventory for the Board of Governors fonds F-33.
Some files may contain personal or confidential information. Access to these files may be restricted as stipulated by Archives policy or the donor. Files marked "pending review" must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release and, as a result of the review, access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the reference archivist for more details.
- Academic Freedom and Tenure, 1966 - 1971; F-209-1; 11 cm of textual records; Title based on contents of the series.
  published
  Series consists of records relating to the creation and revision of the university's Academic Freedom and Tenure statements and policies. Includes reports, examples from other universities, correspondence, and notes to file.
  Textual records
  - Academic freedom and tenure statement, 1966 - 1968; F-209-1-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 209-1)
    Pending review
  - Academic freedom and tenure, 1967 - 1969; F-209-1-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 209-1)
  - Academic freedom and tenure, 1967 - 1969; F-209-1-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 209-1)
  - Academic freedom and tenure, 1970 - 1971; F-209-1-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 209-1)
  - Academic freedom and tenure, 1971; F-209-1-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 209-1)
- Correspondence, 1963 - 1971; F-209-2; 8 cm of textual records
  Series consists of correspondence generated while Richard Lester was both a member of the Board of Governors and also Chairman of the Board.
  - Correspondence - general, 1963 - 1965; F-209-2-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 209-1)
  - Correspondence, 1968 - 1969; F-209-2-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 209-2)
  - Correspondence, 1967 - 1971; F-209-2-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 209-2)
  - Correspondence - Dr. Kenneth Strand appointment as president, 1971; F-209-2-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 209-2)
- Subject files, 1963 - 1985; F-209-3; 19 cm of textual records
  Series consists of subject files relating to Lester's involvement in the architecture and construction of the campus, censure from CAUT, reorganization, resolutions, and a recollection of his time at SFU.
  Textual records; Architectural drawings
  - Architecture & Building, 1963 - 1964; F-209-3-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 209-2)
    Open
  - Board of Governors minutes, vol. 1, 1963 - 1965; F-209-3-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 209-2)
  - Board of Governors minutes, vol. 2, 1963 - 1965; F-209-3-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 209-2)
  - Censure from CAUT, 1967 - 1968; F-209-3-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 209-3)
  - PSA dispute, 1969 - 1970; F-209-3-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 209-3)
  - Reorganization of university structure, 1967 - 1968; F-209-3-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 209-3)
  - Reorganization of university structure, 1967 - 1970; F-209-3-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 209-3)
  - Resolutions of board and faculty flowing from censure, 1968 - 1971; F-209-3-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 209-3)
  - Essay - Richard Lester's recollection of his time at SFU, 1985; F-209-3-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 209-3)
  - Communications between Lester and President Strand, 1968 - 1971; F-209-3-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 209-3)